{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man forced the Armistice of Mudanya upon his enemies, triggering the downfall of David Lloyd George’s government. This man’s opposition to the Treaty of Sevres allowed him to win a more favorable territorial settlement in the Treaty of Lausanne. After consolidating power, this man’s “Six Arrows” ideology promoted a new Latin alphabet for the country and banned the fez. For ten points, name this man who established a new capital at Ankara after founding modern-day Turkey",
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal",
        "Ataturk"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A position outside this city was fortified by Rufus Putnam during one event whose end is celebrated as Evacuation Day. During one battle, Henry Knox reinforced this city’s Dorchester Heights with cannons from Fort Ticonderoga. This city was besieged by American forces following the battles of Lexington and Concord. The Battle of Bunker Hill was fought outside of, for ten points, what Massachusetts city where British troops had earlier committed a namesake massacre?",
      "answer": "Boston"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man arrested William Burroughs after he opposed this man’s plans to sail to the Isle of Terceira. This man destroyed at least 27 Spanish ships at the Bay of C´adiz in the Singeing of the King of Spain’s Beard. This man sacked Santo Domingo and captured Cartagena de Indias in 1586 before fortuitously rescuing Walter Raleigh’s Roanoke Colony. For ten points, name this Elizabethan captain of the Golden Hind who circumnavigated the world from 1577 to 1580.",
      "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s government planned but failed to attack a western neighbor in Project National Glory. Peace Memorial Day commemorates a massacre by this man’s regime known as the 228 Incident. This Commandant of the Whampoa Academy was kidnapped by Zhang Xueliang during the Xi’an Incident, forcing him to collaborate with a group that would later force this husband of Soong Mei-Ling to flee to Taiwan. For ten points, name this leader of the Kuomintang who lost the Chinese Civil War to Mao Zedong.",
      "answer": [
        "Chiang Kai-Shek",
        "Jiang Jieshi,",
        "Chiang Chongchen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Before this event, George Cortelyou attempted to cancel another man’s appearance twice, but was overruled. Roswell Park was driven by “Pan Am” Charlie from Niagara Falls to Buffalo in the wake of this event. Thomas Edison sent an X-ray machine to the victim of this event who was treated at the Milburn House. This event took place at the Temple of Music as part of the Pan-American Exposition. For ten points, name this 1901 event in which Leon Czolgosz [CHO-goss] shot the President of the United States.",
      "answer": "assassination of William McKinley"
    },
    {
      "question": "One book written in this language argued that God did not choose to create the universe, but that his divine nature caused the universe to be. Another book in this language argued that memory is the result of continued abstraction or spiritualization. Another work in this language was criticized by Aquinas for its introduction of the “unity of the intellect.” For 10 points, name this language used by al-Farabi, Averroes, and other Islamic commentators on Aristotle.",
      "answer": [
        "Arabic",
        "al-Arabiyyah",
        "Arabi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city, Ambassador Graham Martin was picked up by “Lady Ace 09” whose crew had orders to arrest him if he attempted to stay. The USS Blue Ridge was so overloaded by one event in this city that its crew began throwing vehicle s into the sea. Irving Berlin’s “White Christmas” was used to begin a series of evacuations in this city that began after the shelling of Tan Son Nhat airport. Operation Frequent Wind was a series of helicopter evacuations of, for ten points, what capital of South Vietnam that was renamed after its fall in 1975?",
      "answer": [
        "Saigon",
        "Ho Chi Minh City before it is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This site included the Mach’ay Cave, where young boys had their ears pierced as a rite of passage. At this site, the Watana Stone was arranged to point at the sun during winter solstices. This site’s other religious buildings included the Room of the Three Windows and the Torreon. Located above the Sacred Valley, this site was discovered when the Urubamba River was traversed by Hiram Bingham’s party. For ten points, identify this “Lost City” of the Incas.",
      "answer": "Macchu Picchu"
    },
    {
      "question": "Vala attempted to flee this battle during fighting at Kalkriese hill. A campaign waged in vengeance for this battle culminated in the Battle of Idistaviso, which was won by Germanicus. This battle’s winning commander led an alliance of tribes including the Cherusci. This battle’s result caused Augustus to rage, “Quintilius Varus, give me back my legions!” Arminius and his German allies inflicted, for ten points, what decisive 9 AD Roman defeat in a namesake forest?",
      "answer": "Battle of the Teutoburg Forest"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a work by this author, a man becomes obsessed with and then terrified by an infinitely long book. When reflecting on a conflict, this author called a war in his country “two bald men fighting over a comb.” This author described a point in space that contains all other points in one work, and described a system of infinite hexagonal rooms in his “Library of Babel.” For ten points, name this author of “The Zahir,” “El Aleph,” and “The Garden of Forking Paths.”",
      "answer": "Jorge Luis Borges"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A picture taken in this location shows Kerry and Caroline Kennedy peeking out of an open door. An item in this location was built from timbers salvaged from a British ship that was abandoned in the Arctic; that piece of furniture was re-installed in this location in 1977, although the C&O Desk was preferred by George H.W. Bush. The Blue Room’s distinctive bowed walls inspired the design of, for ten points, what room in the West Wing of the White House, the primary office space for the President?",
        "answer": "Oval Office"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Kennedy cousins were playing in the Oval Office underneath this desk, whose door was an addition ordered by FDR to conceal his legs. This desk has been used in the Oval Office by every President since Carter except George H.W. Bush.",
        "answer": "HMS Resolute desk"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one work of this type, which ends with the words “horror, horror, horror,” the narrator meets her fianc´e Jean Moraweicki and volunteers at the Union G´en´erale des Isra´elites en France. Another one of these works ends with the lines “the Savichevs are dead. Everyone is dead. Only Tanya is left.” That work was presented at the Nuremburg Trials alongside another work of this type, which was addressed “Dear Kitty” and was written while in hiding in Amsterdam. For ten points, name this type of personal work kept by H´el´ene Berr and Anne Frank.",
        "answer": "World War II diary or journal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "H´el´ene Berr and Anne Frank both died in what concentration camp, just a few days before it became the first major concentration camp liberated by the Allies?",
        "answer": "Bergen-Belsen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Although not Isaiah, similarities with the legend of Sargon of Akkad have led some to believe this book was written in 6th century Babylon. In this book, a group is forced to drink the remains of an idol they made from melted rings, and their leader marries the daughter of Jethro. A leader in this book experiences theophany in the form of a burning bush. For ten points, name this book of the Bible which includes the receiving of the Ten Commandments and Moses’ parting of the Red Sea.",
        "answer": "Book of Exodus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many scholars believe that the biblical Mount Sinai was the Jebel al-Madhbah, a mountain in this present day country ruled by the Hashemite family.",
        "answer": "Jordan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Paul Weber taught many artists from this movement, which was influenced by the Du¨sseldorf School. William Sidney Mount promoted this school as part of the Young America Movement. A poet and a painter stand on a rock and look out at the Catskills in a painting from this movement, Kindred Spirits. For ten points, name this American art movement whose members included Frederic Edwin Church, Asher Durand, and Thomas Cole, named for a New York waterway.",
        "answer": "Hudson River School"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This five-part series by Thomas Cole shows the progression of a civilization from The Savage State to Desolation. This series allegorizes Andrew Jackson and the Democratic Party in the 1830s.",
        "answer": "Course of Empire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2003, David Owen admitted that he suggested assassinating this man. This leader’s Finance Minister Emmanuel Wakhweya defected while visiting London. In 1972, this man ordered the expulsion of all Asians from his country. This leader’s downfall began after he attempted and failed to capture Kagera; this leader was then replaced by Milton Obote after he fled into exile when UNLF and Tanzanian forces captured Kampala. For ten points, name this dictator of Uganda.",
        "answer": "Idi Amin Dada Oumee"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Yonathan Netanyahu died in a raid in this Ugandan city after Idi Amin welcomed the PLFP hijackers of Air France Flight 139 in its international airport.",
        "answer": "Entebbe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man founded the New York Manumission Society and had earlier drafted a state law to abolish slavery. This man served as the U.S. chief negotiator at the Treaty of Paris. In West v. Barnes, this man refused to establish judicial review. The 11th amendment overturned a decision made by this man’s court in Chisholm v. Georgia. This man signed a namesake 1795 treaty with Great Britain. For ten points, name this Founding Father and first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.",
        "answer": "John Jay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Jay authored five essays on “dangers from foreign force and influence” for this collection, published under the pseudonym “Publius”.",
        "answer": "The Federalist Papers"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Angelo Massarelli compiled six unpublished volumes of records from this event. In response to Diogo de Andrada’s criticism of his works, Martin Chemnitz wrote a four-volume examination of this event. Charles Borromeo led the final session of this council, during which the index of forbidden books was published. The spread of Protestantism prompted Pope Paul III to convene, for ten points, what Catholic council that outlined the tenets of the Counter-Reformation?",
        "answer": "Council of Trent or Concilium Tridentinum"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Council of Trent confirmed this doctrine, which stated that the essence of bread and wine becomes the body and blood of Christ. This doctrine was first defined during the Fourth Lateran Council of 1215.",
        "answer": "transubstantiation"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This company’s use of a software tool known as “Greyball” to target law enforcement and other unwanted users contributed to a since-overturned ban of this company in London. This company was founded by Garrett Camp and Travis Kalanick, the latter of whom resigned as CEO in 2017. This technology company, which launched an “Eats” food delivery platform in 2014, controversially operated during a New York City taxi strike. For ten points, name this rideshare company that competes with Lyft.",
        "answer": "Uber Technologies, Inc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Uber is one of several tech companies expected to undergo this process in 2019. This process will allow anyone to purchase stock in the company and allow founders and early employees to cash out their stock.",
        "answer": "Initial Public Offering"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Architecture of Washington, DC",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mansion designed by James Hoban at 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue.",
          "answer": "White House"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of museums surrounding the National Mall, headquartered in a red sandstone “castle” designed by James Renwick.",
          "answer": "Smithsonian Institution"
        },
        {
          "question": "DC-area river whose Mason’s Island was converted into a memorial for Theodore Roosevelt.",
          "answer": "Potomac River"
        },
        {
          "question": "French-born military engineer who created the original plan for the city and lends his name to a Brutalist plaza.",
          "answer": [
            "Pierre Charles L’Enfant",
            "Peter Charles L’Enfant"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sculptor who designed the large seated statue of Abraham Lincoln located in the Lincoln Memorial.",
          "answer": "Daniel Chester French"
        },
        {
          "question": "Free African-American man who assisted Andrew Ellicott with surveying the borders of DC.",
          "answer": "Benjamin Banneker"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gothic Revival house of worship on Wisconsin Avenue, the final resting place of Woodrow Wilson.",
          "answer": [
            "Washington National Cathedral",
            "Cathedral Church of Saint Peter and Saint Paul in the City and Diocese of Washington"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President who lends his name to a large Second French Empire-style “Executive Office Building” on Pennsylvania Avenue.",
          "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Culture in the Second Empire",
      "prompt": "In the Second Empire, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city which was renovated between 1853 and 1870.",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor of the Second Empire.",
          "answer": "Napoleon III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artistic movement founded in the Second Empire which includes Claude Monet.",
          "answer": "Impressionism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of Les Miserables who was exiled to Jersey for criticizing the emperor.",
          "answer": "Victor Hugo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author who described the Second Empire in his Rougon-Macquart Series.",
          "answer": "Emile Zola"
        },
        {
          "question": "Painting by Edouard Manet which was rejected from the 1863 salon for depicting a nude woman with two clothed men and was displayed in the Salon des R´efus´es.",
          "answer": [
            "Luncheon on the Grass",
            "D´ejeuner sur l’Herbe"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Opera house with a ceiling fresco by Marc Chagall which was built by its namesake architect.",
          "answer": "Op´era Garnier"
        },
        {
          "question": "Literary and artistic critic who defended Romanticism and wrote Giselle.",
          "answer": "Th´eophile Gaultier"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Roman Africa",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sea, known as Mare Nostrum [mah-ray noh-strum], that separates Africa from Rome.",
          "answer": "Mediterranean Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "City legendarily founded by Dido and her Phoenician followers.",
          "answer": [
            "Carthage",
            "Cathargo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest of the Greek islands, which was combined with Cyrenaica [SY-reh-NAY-ik-uh] in an African province.",
          "answer": "Crete"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bishop whose conversion from Manichaeism is discussed in his Confessions.",
          "answer": "Saint Augustine of Hippo if “Hippo” is given, you still have to read the next question"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient city where that thinker served as bishop.",
          "answer": [
            "Hippo Reggius",
            "Hippone"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom in Algeria that was unified by Massinissa, known for its skilled light cavalry.",
          "answer": [
            "Numidia",
            "Numidian cavalry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman general who captured Jugurtha, but was not given the accompanying triumph.",
          "answer": "Lucius Cornelius Sulla Felix"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian heresy that arose in Africa in the 4th century AD, arguing that formerly pagan priests could not perform Christian sacraments.",
          "answer": "Donatism"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 2015 study on DNA from this bacteria preserved in human teeth claimed that this bacteria emerged 5,000 years ago and caused pandemics in the Bronze Age. DNA from this bacteria from skeletons in Aschheim Cemetery, Bavaria proved that this bacteria caused a (20 pts)",
        "6th century pandemic. A 2018 model of this bacteria’s transmission argues that fleas and ticks, instead of (10 pts)",
        "rats, were most likely responsible for spreading this bacteria during its most famous pandemic. For ten points, name this bacteria which caused pandemics during Justinian’s reign and the Black Death."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yersinia pestis",
        "plague,",
        "bubonic plague"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Karl Bendetsen co-authored a brief attacking members of this ethnic group. Solicitor General Charles Fahy intentionally withheld the “Ringle Report” which contained FBI and FCC evidence (20 pts)",
        "exonerating this ethnic group. Members of this ethnic group were depicted with large glasses and thin mustaches in racist propaganda cartoons by (10 pts)",
        "Dr. Seuss. John DeWitt’s Executive Order 9066 moved this ethnic group to ten interment camps in 1942. For ten points, name this ethnic group, members of which were the plantiffs in the Hirabayshi and Korematsu cases."
      ],
      "answer": "Japanese-Americans"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Berestov Mount in this city was given to the Monastery of the Caves by Iziaslav Yaroslavich, who faced a 1068 revolt after this city was defeated by the Cumans at the (20 pts)",
        "Alta River. Boleslaw the Great led an expedition to this city during a succession crisis detailed by Nestor in his (10 pts)",
        "Primary Chronicle, a history of a state centered in this city that included that struggle between Sviatopolk and Yaroslav the Wise as well as Grand Prince Vladimir’s conversion to Christianity. For ten points, what capital city of a Rus federation is the modern-day capital of Ukraine?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kiev",
        "Kievan Rus’",
        "Principality of Kiev"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The director of this film began a tradition by staying away from the set for the shooting of its last scene; he was afraid of his crew after filming took 100 more days than expected. Robert Shaw plays the obsessed Quint in this film, which held the record for highest box office gross from (20 pts)",
        "1976 until the release of Star Wars and revolutionized the idea of the summer blockbuster. Martin Brody quips “You’re (10 pts)",
        "gonna need a bigger boat” in, for ten points, what classic thriller with a John Williams score, a Steven Spielberg film about a resort town terrorized by a killer shark?"
      ],
      "answer": "Jaws"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer wrote a mass named for the wife of Francis II, Maria Theresa of Naples and Sicily. A melody by this composer was used for the hymn “God Save Emperor Francis.” This composer’s (20 pts)",
        "“Trauer” symphony is typical of his Sturm und Drang phase. After the Battle of the Nile, this composer’s Mass for Troubled Times was nicknamed for Lord Nelson. A melody from this composer’s (10 pts)",
        "Emperor string quartet is used as the German national anthem. For ten points, name this composer of just over a hundred symphonies with nicknames such as “Farewell” and “Surprise.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Franz Joseph Haydn"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The nobleman Zopyrus cut off his own ears and nose to gain the trust of rebels in this city who had revolted against Darius I. A ruler of this city allied with the Larsa during a campaign against the (20 pts)",
        "Elamites. This city was conquered by the Persians after Nabonidus lost the Battle of Opis. The (10 pts)",
        "Ishtar Gate was commissioned by this city’s king Nebuchadnezzar II, who deported Jews in this city’s namesake Captivity. Home to the Hanging Gardens, for ten points, name this Mesopotamian city-state whose most famous ruler promulgated the Code of Hammurabi."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Babylon",
        "Babylonia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man led a colonial force that fought alongside Mingo soldiers led by Tanacharison, who supposedly washed his hands in the brains of an opposing leader. This man remarked that “I (20 pts)",
        "heard the bullets whistle and, believe me, there is something charming in the sound” in a letter to his brother John in May 1754 after a battle in which (10 pts)",
        "Joseph Coulon de Villiers died. Roughly a month after the Battle of Jumonville Glen, this Lieutenant Colonel surrendered at Fort Necessity. For ten points, name this American colonial leader who, years later, decidedly did not surrender as Commander-in-Chief of the Continental Army."
      ],
      "answer": "George Washington"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of the all-female Cumann na mBan [man] that participated in this event, Elizabeth O’Farrell, negotiated the end of this event. A ship disguised as the (20 pts)",
        "SS Aud failed to deliver weapons to this event. Michael Mallin led forces on Saint Stephen’s Green during this event, after which one side’s leaders were executed at (10 pts)",
        "Killingham Gaol. Those leaders included Joseph Plunkett and Patrick Pearse, who led the Volunteers during this event. The General Post Office was occupied in, for ten points, what 1916 insurrection that tried to establish an independent Ireland?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Easter Rising",
        "Rebellion"
      ]
    }
  ]
}